This next presentation on the Ed Gray purple motor, I guess
kind of been a long time coming.
I know that when these motors were first made available,
the blue one that Alphrae and Corr has and the purple one
here,
I think John Riley, who somehow got his hands on them
through some estate deal or whatever,
I was basically the first person, I believe, that he
contacted to purchase these motors.
At that time, I didn't have the money and didn't have that
much interest in these particular motors
because I didn't really understand the whole history of
what was going on.
But the whole Ed Gray story kind of in my world kind of
happened in the early 2000s.
Peter had come out with a book called The Free Energy Secrets
of Cold Electricity,
which I guess you could say is kind of his thesis on how he
saw the technology working.
And then soon after that, John Bedini said, well, you
essentially have it correct.
Here's my drawings.
John Bedini went and visited Ed Gray with his friend and
partner Marvin Cole years ago.
I'm sorry, Ron Cole.
Too many Coles.
And with him and Ron Cole and they were able to analyze and
look at it.
And John had written up multiple diagrams on the gray motor,
the gray tube, how it was switching.
There was this interesting diode that everybody said he
drew in the wrong direction, which he didn't.
At that time, when I looked at the drawings, I didn't know
too much about it or how a diode really was supposed to
work.
And that was the only thing that ever really made sense to
me and is how I came up with a little plasma ignition
circuit,
which is kind of an analogy of that circuit.
After a while, Alphrey and Cora wound up with the blue
motor.
Reggie has had this one quite a while.
I think Reggie contacted me years ago about this.
And right around the same time, Mark McKay, where after
John put out those drawings,
somebody named Gary McGratton had been doing some
experiments and posted it online and said,
if anybody writes him, he'll send his report of his
experiments.
And when I contacted Gary McGratton and he sent it to me
and he saw I was in Spokane, Washington,
he said, hey, there's somebody else in Spokane, Washington,
experimenting with this.
So he put me in touch with Mark McKay, took my friend Jeff
out there.
Jeff happened to know Mark's one of his family members.
And Mark had given me a few parts to experiment with.
And I think we went into the back of one of the trailers
that was kind of a setup where Mark was doing some
experiments.
And from then, Mark was so passionate about trying to get
to the answer of what this gray motor business is about.
And went on a journey for, I guess, several years meeting
gray family members, engineers, investors,
trying to get to the bottom of the story.
He's presented, I believe, two times on eMediaPress. com.
There's the history of the EV gray motor.
You can find that on eMediaPress if you want to see his
previous two presentations.
This particular presentation is going to be specifically
the history of this particular motor,
because each color-coded motor has its own very unique
history.
Mark is the world's leading authority on the history of the
EV gray technology.
And actually 12-plus years of analysis of this unique free
energy phenomenon has opened up new possibilities into
reverse engineering,
this powerful yet lost discovery.
Mr. McKay has 35 years of engineering experience in
industrial power and control systems.
He received a bachelor's in science in electrical
engineering from New Mexico State in 1974,
and is a professional engineering in the state of
Washington.
Please welcome Mark McKay.
This one here.
Well, good morning, all you fine faces.
Thank you for getting up early in the morning and coming to
see this.
Kind of give you a short overview here.
Many of you have furnaces or air conditioners in your house.
All the motors that are in those devices have a quantity
called COP of about 0. 41.
COP stands for Coefficient of Performance.
Basically, it's a measure of how much energy goes into the
motor
and how much effective energy comes out to move air through
your house.
Now, the great breakthrough you were able to demonstrate
this morning was Reggie's Reluctance Motor,
which is a great improvement on the technology.
It has a COP of 0. 91 from just recent laboratory
evaluations.
I mean, that's going to cut the energy usage of motors from
what they are classically now
for a single-phase induction motor.
Well, cut it in half.
And even just a half of what's currently used for motors
is going to be a huge boom to energy reduction.
This technology is something else.
At the peak of its development, this motor was producing a
COP of 300.
I mean, that's science fiction.
The technology here is strictly non-classical.
You can't use your...
It has a lot of things that use classical calculations,
so you've got to at least know your basic electronics to
work it.
But once it reaches the non-classical event, I call it the
radiant event,
you're off into another world.
And not very many people, least of all myself, have been
able to figure out what that is.
Now, Reggie's motor out there, that is a classical magnetic
process.
This is something else.
The forces that are generated in this device are three
orders of magnitude greater
than what you can achieve with a classical magnetic field,
if we have yet to know what that is.
So this is an age-changing technology.
If it wasn't destroyed or wasn't ruined accidentally by
ignorance,
we'd be living in a completely different world.
And if we can ever crack the nut as to how this thing did
its thing back then,
we would be living in a new world.
The whole energy, oil issue, and all the geopolitical
processes
would probably be vastly different.
So I'd like to go over the history of how this particular
motor came about
and kind of broadly touch on the overall technology
that was developed and then lost.
Okay, so this is the purple motor.
This is what it looks like from the side.
Okay, this motor was not made in isolation.
It is the fifth generation of a whole series of motors
that started construction in about 1971.
It was based by an inventor named Marvin Cole.
This is the earliest picture I could get of that motor.
I don't know what the EMA-1 and the EMA-2 look like,
and I don't even know for sure if they ever existed.
But this is where it started.
This one was about 1971.
Then he came up with some better ideas,
and he developed the EMA-4.
This one here is the one that sets it apart
from any other free energy technologies you might have been
exposed to.
This device was tested at Caltech by a company called Crosby
Research
that actually specialized in testing inventions.
They consulted with two PhD electrical engineers that
worked for the Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
These guys specialized in power supplies.
They worked on this thing for 10 days and made all these
measurements.
That's where they came up with the calculations of the COP
of 300.
So I don't think very many other free energies are vetted
to that particular degree
and come up with this kind of performance.
Then Marvin Cole left the project.
It's been speculated by me that he discovered there was an
anti-gravity process here,
and that was too much for him to handle.
So then Gray, who was the promoter and money man,
hired a classically trained engineer named Richard Hackenberger
that got his degree at Southern University, his master's,
and was working in Silicon Valley.
His specialty was transistors and making things like that.
Well, he took that technology that Marvin Cole had,
and he built his own motor.
This was called the EMA-6, which was on display in 1976.
Unfortunately, he had a few bugs to work out.
This thing here, when it was demonstrated, it only put out
two horsepower.
So later he was working on it.
They finally got it going pretty good,
but when this thing, with this non-classical process that
generates all these forces,
also generates a lot of EMI.
So the FCC descended upon them, confiscated all the motor,
run it through a shredder, and it was never seen again.
Well, that didn't deter him.
In 1979, Gray and Mr. Hackenberger, and Gray's oldest son,
Mark Gray,
got a huge grant to go to Dodge City, Kansas,
and manufacture this whole series of motors.
And you can see the purple motor is right here.
But you have the white motor, the gold motor, the black
motor,
and there was a blue motor that's not pictured here,
and one at the end, and I don't know what it is.
And then another motor that's not pictured.
It's just the case.
So this was the zenith of the technology.
Each one of these motors were designed to explore a
particular aspect of this technology.
They were trying to really branch out.
The black motor at the end here just has one set of poles,
and it's got an opening on the side so you can actually see
the timing
and the effect of what's going on inside the motor.
The purple motor here was designed to have everything plus
an energy recollection system.
The white motor was all plastic.
The gold motor was the same as the purple motor,
except it didn't have the energy recollection.
And the one down at the end, I don't know what it is.
It looks like the first prototype they built just to get
started.
Okay, now we'll go into the actual history.
It's the best I could determine what happened.
This kind of took place all over the country.
Okay, this is Richard Hackenberger, a photo that was taken
in 1973.
Here he's demonstrating a popping coil device for a
technical reporter.
This is the man that actually designed this motor and had
it built.
I'm sure we'd like to meet him.
This is where they did it, in Dodge City, Kansas.
This is where the money man was.
And this is the money man.
As far as I can tell from the number of people he was
hiring,
the number of machines he built,
paying for room and board and motel for Gray and Hackenberger
and his son.
They had a little company going there too,
and there was a mad dash to buy all this stock.
So that's a whole business scandal in itself.
But anyway, he saw this and it just blew his socks off.
He had the money and the time to really dig into this.
And he was a critical player in this whole saga right up to
the end.
Well, there was a financial dispute with the players and
what was going on.
Everybody was trying to get ownership and control over the
technology.
There was no patents produced for any of this stuff.
So whoever had it had the golden goose.
Well, Gray and Mr. Hackenberger decided that they've had
enough.
They're going to take all their motors, load them up in a
truck.
So on Christmas Eve, in a very cold winter, they loaded it
up and hauled ass out of town
and hid out in Portland, Oregon for six months or so.
They eventually ended up in Canyon Country.
But it was a very cold trip.
And Mark Gray describes how Mr. Hackenberger was trying to
get the fuel nozzle to fuel up the truck
and couldn't do it because he was compromised by the
temperatures
and probably the stress of having to stay up all night and
drive across country.
Well, unfortunately, that exposure, he got sick, he got the
flu,
and he died when they were somewhere in the Portland area.
His family, who was also in Oregon, didn't know about his
death for like a month.
And so all that expertise, all that knowledge was lost.
His brother eventually ended up with his lab notebook.
But after 10 years, nobody was interested in it, so he
tossed it.
But he did remember one sentence, and he had notes in his
book that said,
this stuff works, but I don't know why.
So that points to the non-classical nature of what they ran
across.
Well, Gray, he's not going to let a good thing go to waste.
He took all the motors, to which there was about six or
seven of them in that truck,
and set up shop in Canyon Country, which was right there.
That was American Home Medical Equipment.
Because obviously, Mr. Audrey was trying to hunt him down
to get his $2 million investment back.
But the motors, for some reason, didn't work, or at least
they didn't work as well as they should.
He had problems.
Mr. Gray was not a technical person.
He didn't even know Ohm's Law.
So he thought that he could just go right out and hire a
technician off the street,
and say, go fix that motor.
I want it running.
Okay, well, so this gentleman here, Mr. Nelson Schloff, who
I had the fortune to interview in 2006,
took the job out of the newspaper.
His background was he was an aviation electronics
technician.
Well, the sad part is, Mr. Gray did not tell Mr. Schloff
what the purpose of this technology was.
He was told it was going to be an electric motor for cars,
and he wanted him to get it running.
So he looked at that thing, and at the time, the motor had
been running.
Gray hired another engineer, also named Richard, that was
able to figure out how to work it and get it going.
And the original motor itself had thyrotrons on it that
were used to trigger the ignitrons.
Mr. Schloff decided that, well, you can't have thyrotrons
on there because this is going to be in a car,
and it's going to vibrate and going to mess up those thyrotrons.
I don't know what the vibration would do on the ignitron,
but apparently that wasn't an issue.
So then he looked at the electromagnets that are in this
motor and decided,
oh, this wire is way too fine.
You can't get enough current through this.
So he went to the machine shop next door, and he had them
completely rewire the electromagnets.
He told me that the original wire on these electromagnets
were about 19, 18 gauge,
maybe even as small as 24 gauge.
He wasn't sure.
But he figured that he needed 14 gauge wire in there.
So he took out all the wires, rewound them as simple solenoids
with 14 gauge wire, hooked it up,
and by golly, now the motors would start from zero speed,
and they'd go in the opposite direction.
Well, that's good and great.
The only problem was it took 10 kilowatts of power to run
this motor in that configuration with no load.
But to Gray, that didn't matter.
The thing started, and it went backwards and forwards, and
he thought he was ready to go.
Well, Rocky never knew until I interviewed him 23 or 6
years later that the whole purpose of this technology was
free energy.
He had absolutely no clue at all.
So, inadvertently, he went and destroyed all these
prototypes completely, unknowingly, and innocently trying
to do his job
because Gray didn't have enough technical expertise or
enough management ability to steer him in the right
direction.
But Gray at the time thought he'd really cut a fat cow.
So he goes on to try and sell these motors across the
country
because he had the lab reports from the Crosby research
that was done at Caltech, which was very impressive.
And then they had a whole bunch of research reports from
their work at Dodge City,
where it was tested, and that's what caused the big
financial fervor there.
You can see in this video here he's trying to sell these
three lab reports that he's got
that have all this great and wonderful information.
I'm sure they did, but probably nobody believed him
because he didn't have a motor that could perform that good.
So he gets the idea that he's going to go and sell this
stuff to the Jewish community in Israel.
And apparently they had some interest, so he flew over
there and made his presentation.
And what the real problem was, Gray was not willing in
selling the technology outright.
He was trying to sell licenses because he figured he could
make more money selling licenses and leases
and doing that work than actually letting go of the
technology.
He was so afraid that once any of these things got out,
somebody else would take advantage of the simplicity of the
technology that was in this motor,
and he'd be out in the cold, which is probably a fair, fair
assessment.
But it didn't sell.
So he came back empty-handed.
They offered him $9 million for an outright sale of what he
had.
And we didn't go for it.
That was the end of the negotiations.
Then he got the idea he was going to sell all this stuff to
Congress.
So he wrote a personal letter to every member of Congress
saying,
hey, I got this great, wonderful thing, and I'll give it to
you.
But nobody was interested because nobody believed the
stories,
and I don't know if they even took the time to take a look
at the lab reports.
So that fell on its nose.
Well, after failing at that, his health was really marginal
at best.
He was a chain smoker, and by the time that came around, he
was on oxygen.
He was in and out of the hospital several times for lung
problems.
And then one day at the shop that he had at Sparks, Nevada,
some high schooler was running a stick along the outside
corrugated metal of the building
at 2 in the morning or something like that.
So he ran out there to confront the prankster, apparently
took a gun with him.
He was going to fire a warning shot in the air.
The gun didn't work.
So in panic, he came back in and collapsed in the living
room.
He forgot to take his oxygen bottle.
At least that's the story as relayed by the lady he was
living with at the time.
So that was the end of Gray.
But Russell Audrey, the guy who paid for all those motors,
was hot on the trail,
and he demanded to get those motors back.
So there was these legal disputes that took place over a
few years,
and getting into more drama, these things finally were
collected
and went back to Dodge City.
And Russell Audrey put him in a shop and hired as many
people as he could
to get these things running again.
He hired Nelson Schloff.
He hired Gray's oldest son.
And they worked on this for about one, two years.
I'm not sure exactly how long, but they couldn't get any
place with it.
The secret was so well contained that even all these people
had been around it intimately for years
didn't have a clue.
In my interview with Mark Gray, who lives over in eastern
Washington,
said that he wished he'd paid more attention to what was
going on at the time.
Well, after these motors sat in a barn for a while, a guy
named Kenneth Hawkins talked to the lawyer
of the firm at the time and found out where at least some
of them were at.
So he drove up to Dodge City and was able to acquire the
white motor and the black motor,
the casing for the E3 motor, the pump, and a few other odds
and ends.
And he brought these back to his friend at the time, Norm Wooten,
who put together a very nice presentation in 2002 showing
the parts and pieces
and making his comments on it.
It was 2000?
I thought it was 2002.
Okay, well, whatever.
It was in that time frame.
Okay, I stand corrected.
It was in Dallas?
It wasn't in Florida.
Okay.
It was a great presentation.
He did a real good job.
He had all the parts and pieces taken apart there.
He made his assessment because he's into free energy
research.
of one particular brand or another.
And apparently it didn't generate any interest,
so he had all these motor parts laying around.
And about a year later, he decided to sell them.
So he sold them to Al Francor up in Canada,
yeah, Canada, the guy with the solar cell system that Peter
helped build.
And he's been working on them and checking them out
and trying to restore them by buying hard-to-get parts and
pieces for them,
like these ignitrons, the capacitors.
And he's got those two motors.
Well, the other, this gold motor, I mean, the gold motor,
the purple motor,
and the great big, huge power supply that drove these
things ended up being brokered out to John Riley,
who's also a free energy researcher, spiritual meditation-type
guy who has his own business doing this stuff.
He hired another engineer that came in for a very hefty fee,
analyzed all the motors, at least one of them,
came up with a 30-page report of all the wiring diagrams
and his estimate of what was going on,
which was, again, purely a classical evaluation,
and came to the conclusion they couldn't do anything with
it.
So he put these things up for sale.
The original cost of this motor and the gold motor was like
$30,000.
And I think the trigger cart where he thought the secret
was, was $125,000.
I think that one's still for sale.
I'm not sure.
It is?
Okay.
Al, on the other hand, was doing windmill motors.
And there was a company that was really interested in that,
and they went and bought the gold motor for him to work on,
hoping that he could move it ahead.
So Al ended up with the gold motor, the black motor, and
the white motor.
And Reggie bought the purple motor in 2013.
I don't know how much he paid for it, but it was
substantial.
Okay, so that's basically who built it, where it was built,
when it was built,
how it got destroyed.
So now we'll go on to the importance of why this is so
important.
Well, I kind of alluded to that.
Spoiler alert.
Okay, the keystone to this whole technology rests in the
work that was done
by the two PhD electrical engineers at Caltech.
And these guys, these two engineers, at least one of them,
was hired to write the patent for it.
And then he went on, and he was still working at JPL,
and he ran into Reggie some years later, telling Reggie,
hey, this is what you've got to look into.
But he was totally impressed.
In fact, both of these engineers became members of the
board
of the company that Gray had at the time.
Intergrave Enterprises, and they had another name to it.
They also had a call, they called it Electrotech.
So they were wheeling and dealing with corporations.
Okay, so this is the crux of the matter.
Most people, when they deal with free energy engines,
they're using electricity, and then they get classical
electricity out,
and hopefully they get more out than what they get in.
This technology is not that way.
Its free energy output is torque or force.
So here you have the converter right up here.
It takes two batteries.
Can't have one, you have to have two.
Here is the converter, called the engine.
It was always called a motor.
It's not a motor.
And it went and drove a classical generator.
So here we have,
these are the measured numbers that they reported on.
This whole thing took 26. 8 watts in,
and came up with 7. 5 kilowatts out.
And they ran this for as long as the energy in the battery
would last,
which was a day and a half or something like that.
Apparently, they didn't have the switching system set up
there,
so it would charge one battery and then swap it over to the
other.
But I don't think there's any,
has anybody else heard of a free energy technology in today's
market
that has these kind of specifications?
I don't think anybody's come close to it.
That's why,
I did some calculations once,
and I could be correct,
but that's like filling up your car once
and being able to drive it for five years.
That's paying your power bill on your house for one month
and live in it for five years.
This is the sort of power energy gains we're giving here.
But actually, since you could recycle that,
you wouldn't have to fill up your car again
or power your house again.
Okay, so now we'll get more into the technical aspects.
That's probably what you're all wanting to know what's
happening.
We'll look at the sister, the gold motor,
because I've got more information on that than I do this
one.
They're very close.
Like I said, Al Francoeur up in Canada has the gold motor,
and he spent hours and hours taking it apart
and drawing schematics up, detailed schematics,
and then shared them at the convention a few years ago.
And I took those hand-drawn drawings
and used AutoCAD and made some readable schematics.
Okay, this is the gold motor as he got it.
I don't think it had the batteries on it.
Here's the elevation.
You can see that they're very similar.
The only thing that's different is the coloring on the end
bell.
Okay, the gold motor has the commentator,
which is a mysterious component trying to figure out how it
works.
But this commentator, they made five of them,
one for each of those prototype motors.
So they were able to get some savings there
by using the same set of drawings at the same machine shop
to knock out five of them.
Here's what happens.
The purple motor doesn't have the end bell that's being
taken off there
so you can see what's on the inside of it.
Okay, so here's the contactor points are wired just like
they're shown here,
except there's 15 contacts,
and not all of them are being used.
When Mr. Schlaff rewound that,
he took off everything that he didn't need and left it.
So there's a whole lot of control points there
that serve some purpose in the original motor
that we don't know about, unfortunately.
And if he tried to figure out why he wired the ones up he
did,
I can't figure that out either.
Here's the end bell coming off.
This is the stator electromagnets.
Here's the rotor.
Here's the ignitron array, which looks just like this.
Here's a close-up of one of the ignitrons.
These were used in spot welding quite a bit.
Al was probably able to get the last few available on the
Internet.
Okay, this is, I don't know if you can see that,
but this is my interpretation of Al's handwritten drawings
of how the schematic went together.
It was pretty simple.
All the rotor and the stator electromagnets were fired at
the same time.
They were fired on the low side with these ignitrons.
The upper ignitrons serve the purpose of charging these
capacitors.
Now, you can see at the top where the power comes in at 5,000
volts.
That 5,000 volts came from a 50-kilowatt cart
that was basically two huge Variax and a large rectifier
and a 5,000 volt transformer.
It was a huge monster.
It took a 50-kilowatt generator just to run that thing.
When Gray demonstrated these motors
when they were somewhat operational in Kansas,
they just plug it into an outlet
to get the excitation power to run it.
When he came back five years later,
after these things had been butchered,
he had to rent this generator
in order to get these things to even turn.
And he didn't even know the difference.
Originally, the ignitrons were fired by, like I say, thyrotrons.
Nelson Schloff came up with this approach here
where he took a Zener diodes,
made a long string out of them,
took the 5,000 volts and cut it down to 1,500 volts,
which is the trigger voltage for these ignitrons,
which I think is, you know, it's an improvement there.
It's a lot better than trying to manage thyrotrons.
I don't know about the speeds
and I don't know if there's other parameters to be involved,
but that was an improvement.
And those devices are these little cards that are stuck in
here.
So he uses the commentator to trigger the card
and from there it triggers the ignitron.
What's odd about this whole thing
is this capacitor charging network.
Now notice these ignitrons up here
have to be triggered by a transformer
because they're on the high side of the load.
And what he's got is the power supply comes in,
keeps these two capacitors charged,
and then at various times
during the control of the commentator's operation,
it charges up this bank of four capacitors.
So these things get charged with a pulse
and then a few little few degrees more rotation
on the commentator.
There are these turned on
and these capacitors are discharged through the motor.
Why he did it that way?
I don't know,
but at the time I asked him what was going on,
this was before I had the schematic,
and he said that when he got the motors,
they were doing this funky capacitor charging system
with the ignitrons,
except he said there was a battery in there
and they were charging it from the negative end.
And he thought he'd keep the same system.
He kind of reworked it into this,
but previously there was some sort of system
or some sort of energy recovering system
that required the high current capacity of an ignitron
and the battery was involved.
He took the battery out because he didn't know what it was
for.
So this is what we ended up today
and this is probably how this,
the purple motor was also reconfigured in 1979.
Some of the,
also an interesting thing is you'll notice
there's all these jacks on the side here,
a bunch here,
a bunch in the front.
These things were configured not as complete systems,
but as test systems.
And all the various subsystems came out on these jacks
so you could hook it up this way
and you could hook it up that way
and you could put a meter here
and you could put a meter there.
It was primarily,
it was still a evaluation presentation.
So some of the other systems,
this was the charging system.
Now,
this particular technology,
for reasons I'll explain later,
you have to,
you can't start the motor from zero speed.
You have to speed it up to a minimum of 500 RPM.
Okay,
so they were able to use a generator
which also served,
a generator that could also be used as a starter.
So in one configuration,
you'd turn it on as a start motor,
get this thing going up to 500 RPM,
have it working in mode,
then you could take the energy off the shaft
and run a generator
to recharge some of the batteries.
And this was how they did it.
Here's a detail of the Ignatron trigger card.
Here's showing the outboard relays,
which have been removed from this box here
because they're not necessary
for the main technology involved.
Then Nelson Schloff built a timing box.
At the time,
I knew what it did,
but it wasn't important.
It had to do with how long you turn things,
which wasn't necessary.
But anyway,
he had this timing control box
for startup and shutdown.
Here's more details of the commentator.
And this is what's interesting.
This is the design of the actual cores.
This was done,
taken apart on the black motor.
And Al Francor put this online.
It shows some unique stuff there.
These are open core coils.
These are not closed core coils
like what you have in an induction motor.
This is much like the induction coils,
like your ignition coil,
things like that.
With the open core design
and you don't have a complete magnetic path,
it reduces the K factor
between the primary
and the secondary windings.
But you can still look at the shape there
and go,
what the heck?
There's a purpose for that,
in my opinion.
So here's kind of the overall power windings.
That's a little simpler
from that first diagram.
Also,
Mr. Schlough added
this huge custom-made diode
and he described the shop
that made it
in Thousand Oaks
is where this thing was made.
And how one of them broke open
and had four diodes
and then had the compensating resistor
and compensating capacitor.
And that was repeated about eight times
and that's how they make the diode.
He said the original diodes
that came in here
that served in this location
were much, much smaller.
But in order for him
to handle the current
with his now massive 14-gauge coils,
he needed something bigger
to do suppression.
Okay, now we can get into
the differences
between the gold motor
and the purple motor
that I'm aware of.
Because there is a big difference.
From the outside,
now let's see.
they look pretty much the same.
Now this is comparing
the gold motor
with the white motor
showing the similarity
among these engines
that were built in 79.
They all have three stator poles.
This is what's inside
the purple motor
if we were to take
the front cover off.
What you're looking at,
these big coils here,
are coils,
are supplementary coils
that are independent
and isolated
from the actual
much smaller stator coils
that are on the inside.
This is an energy recovery
system that has its history
way back in the technology.
Here's the rotor.
The rotor looks pretty much
the same as it does
in the gold motor.
Okay, here's the picture
of those energy recovery coils
with the rotor taken out.
So you can see
how big they are
compared to the...
This is the energy recovery coil
and here's the actual stator coil.
Yeah, the iron,
it's got this part here,
this brown part,
that's actually laminated
iron cords.
I mean, I think
it's impressive.
I wonder how much it cost
to have those things
made in the 79.
As far as we can tell,
this is how it was wired,
sort of,
and even then we don't know.
I mean,
they're not simple coils either.
They've got this
funky doodle
three coil system.
At least this is what
Reggie has been able
to determine
from doing
ohmic measurements.
So,
a lot more mysteries there.
But to me,
this resembles
the topology
of the stubble field coil.
Here we have
the active coil.
This would be the stator.
And this is those
energy recovery coils
on the outside.
Because we're working
with a non-classical energy,
so all our
classically trained ideas
about
electromagnetic induction
and all that sort of stuff
don't apply here.
It would be nice
if they did.
Okay,
so this goes back,
this concept
of having your central coil
and then having
an energy recovery coil
around it
goes back to
where these were
photos taken
by Tom Valone
in 1973.
But,
Valentine.
Valentine,
there we go.
In the corner there,
which didn't show
in the other picture,
is this little
supplementary
demonstration thing.
You can see here,
at least I can see it,
is one of those
stator coils.
And around the outside
is this much heavier
thick wire
that forms the same
sort of configuration
we see in the purple motor.
Finally got implemented
in the purple motor,
but they were thinking
about it,
at least Marvin Cole
was,
way back then.
And,
to top it off,
in the 1975 patent,
they actually show it.
They don't describe it,
they didn't say
what it is
or how it worked,
but here's this
illustration that's provided.
And we'll show
that in each
of these poles,
they got three
separate coil
sets.
So two coil sets
are in the middle
and the one
much larger coil set
is on the outside.
To me,
that shows
the same sort of
arrangement
that we see
in the purple motor,
except here
they were trying
to get it all together
in one pole piece.
Once Richard
Hackenberger
developed this,
he probably found out
he needed to make it
much bigger
for high voltage
isolation
and other
engineering reasons.
But this whole
energy recovery system
might have been
the foundation
of the
mysterious floating
flux coil,
flux field,
which is on the
outside of the
early motors.
This is a model
of the EMA-4
and here you have
this harness
on the outside
with all these
coils of wire.
In the patent,
it shows that they
are connected
to the charging
capacitors.
So I suspect
it's an energy
recovery system
that worked
to some degree.
Now you can see
these things
on the EMA-4.
This is actually
the E-2 motor.
Originally,
they only had
one loop
of coax wire
for each power supply.
Here,
Mr. Hackenberger
has doubled it
to two,
so he went from
one kind of coax
to another kind
of coax.
If you look
through the photographs,
there's actually
proof that those
were all
individual wires.
It wasn't one coil,
one continuous coil.
It's actually
nine individual coils.
And this is how
they fit into
the power supply diagram
that was supplied
in the 1975 patent,
which is kind of
different because
how much induction
can you get
in one turn
of coax shielded wire?
So this is another
indication that
whatever he was
dealing with here
was non-classical
in nature.
And it permeated
the motor.
It came from
the electromagnets,
went through
that three-quarter
inch aluminum case
and was still able
to be absorbed
with that small
surface area
and still have
the ability
to charge
or partially
charge these
capacitors.
There was a lot
of static
electricity.
Some observers
of this motor
when it was running
said that it would
just draw your hair
right to it.
So it was kind of
like a Vandy-Gaff
generator,
which a Vandy-Gaff
generator that can
do that has to
charge up to about
300,000 volts
or so.
It's all
electrostatic,
but that's what
they had on the
case of the motor.
Also, the same
observer said that
when this thing
ran, it made
a hellacious noise.
Well, with all the
arcs and sparks,
I can certainly
see that.
Okay.
Now we'll get down
to the part that
you probably all
want to know.
What's the hidden
secrets that I have
been able to
determine through
my investigation
of all the photos
and interviews
and things that I've
been able to do?
So these are the
top four.
Okay, the first
thing we were led
to believe in the
patent, in the
1975 patent, that
we're dealing with
a simple solenoid
opposing electromagnets.
Wrong.
Here's that same
picture of
Hackenberger with
the popping coil.
That coil has got
at least three
conductors on it.
That's not a
simple solenoid.
Here's another shot
showing another
demonstration.
And there, you
can hardly see them,
but there's two
wires heading up
here.
These also have
three conductors,
wires going into
them.
So with that
topology, this is
the corrected
drawing.
This is kind of
what they had.
This probably
doesn't show all
of it.
Maybe there's more
windings.
I don't know,
but at least
that's basically.
Now if we go
back and look at
the early
popping coil
demonstrations,
before they built
the motor, they
had these popping
coils because they
didn't have the
money to build
the motor.
In fact, it's
alleged that Gray
got the idea
from somebody who
alleged that
worked for Tesla.
His name was
Andre Popov.
And he was
either demonstrating,
selling these things,
or giving this thing
to Gray where
you put this
little coil here
without the
rocket on it.
And you pop it
off, and with
the regular
power supply,
it would jump
about 20 inches
or so.
You hook up
the magic power
supply.
It would go up,
hit the ceiling,
and put a dent
in it.
This shows you
that whatever
kind of power
they were putting
into that coil
a second time
around was
vastly different.
They called it
cold electricity.
Well, if you
take a closer
look at this,
you'll see that
those electromagnets
each took
four conductors.
These are not
simple solenoids.
Why they took
four conductors
is, my guess,
is as good
as anybody else's
at the moment.
Maybe we'll figure
it out more
conclusively as
we go on.
So, this is my
best guess of how
things actually were.
Here we have
the, these are
transformers here.
They have a minor
electromagnetic coil
which acts as a
current limiter here
which also decreases
the K value
of the transformers
so that the primary
and the secondary
are free to
oscillate as they
will.
And here I show
that the, it's a,
the arc between
the cores.
I'll talk to that
a little bit more
here in just a moment.
Okay, that gets us
to hidden secret
number two.
Okay, here's a
picture from 1973
Sacanetti article
showing Gray
pointing to that
little window.
That little window
didn't exist on
the previous motor.
In fact, it didn't
exist on this motor
for quite a while,
at least through
the early photos.
They had to stop,
take this thing
apart, take the
inch and a half
plate off the
front of that motor,
send it out to a
machine shop to mill
that two inch
by three inch
window and then
put the whole thing
back together.
Then they had to
cut a notch out
of the arm that
held their air
compressor in order
to see through it.
Now the question
is, what in the
heck are they
looking at?
They certainly
don't need to
look at it for
speed.
My conclusion
was they were
actually looking at
the arcs that
were being generated
between the pole
faces.
In fact, the air
compressor there has
to constantly blow
air into the
engine so all
the chemistries
that's developed
from the arcs
are gotten rid
of all the
nitrous oxide
and that sort
of stuff.
So that's
where I got
on the idea.
So then if you
look at the
patent, the
zero degree
reference is
right when
these two
minor magnets
are right in
that position.
So I assume
that was where
the arc was
struck and then
as the motor
runs, the arc
is stretched
over this
insulator
and at some
point it's
eventually got
to quench
or be
disconnected.
So then they
go on to the
next one.
In the purple
motor, you
don't have all
those electromagnets.
It's a much
simpler design.
So if you
look at this
one, I figure
boy that looks
an awful lot
like one is
providing the
arc against
the other one
there with that
sharp point
and the other
one having
kind of a
rounded nose.
That's merely
speculation on
my part.
But if you
look back
at these,
the wire
capacitor is
actually connected
with a crimp
terminal to the
core phase for
the purpose of
this demonstration.
So they were
electrifying the
cores.
So getting back
to the previous
drawing, that's
where this come
from.
They discharge the
capacitor through
this network that
charges up and
produces a huge
current going
through this
shorted secondary
loop.
Well then, at a
particular time
after the current
has had the time
to reach maximum
current, this
circuit is broken
by means of the
arc being pulled
apart.
That is when the
magic happens.
That's when the
non-classical event
takes place, as far
as I can determine.
It just so happens
at the same time
when the stubble
field device does
its magic.
Okay, now we go
into hidden secret
number three.
The second battery.
This is the one
that's been overlooked.
Peter had it
figured out, though.
In the beginning,
when they were
doing the popping
coil stuff, they
had to have two
batteries to run
their power supply.
Why do they have
to have two
batteries?
Well, it was
alleged so that
you use the power
from one, you
charge it for the
other, and then
you switch them,
is what the line
was given to the
observers and
potential investors.
This in itself
was a pretty
impressive device.
It was a switch
mode power supply
that used
old chopper
vibrators.
Today, we'd be
calling it a
switching power
supply, but it
was a mechanical
one back then.
But he probably
had it wired up
differently to take
it to the age
of getting a lot
of high-voltage
feedback current.
They show
1,400 watts
of connected load
here with those
10 light bulbs.
I don't think
those light bulbs
were lit up
to full capacity
because I'm sure
they each weren't
putting out
1,600 lumens.
But they lit up
to the point
that you could
say, yeah,
they're lit up.
What was interesting
is the light
that those things
put out was
white.
A regular
incandescent lamp
when it's not
running at full
voltage capacity
or full current
capacity, it kind
of glows orange
in that area.
For some reason,
these things were
able to put out
white light.
I don't know
if they were
arcing on the
inside or what
was happening,
but he had all
these light bulbs
hanging on the
ceiling.
Then he'd run
a TV,
an electric razor,
and a drill
just to show
him that this
particular power
could run
these other
things.
Well, the output
of this converter
was measured
at a radio station
by one of his
salesmen
and shown
that it was
a square wave
output that
operated at about
5 kilohertz.
So it's pulsating
DC at about
1,300 volts
is what the output
of this thing
was that could
be measured
classically.
I'm not sure
if...
I'm sure
this thing here
integrated some
of the characteristics
that they have
in the motor.
Originally,
all the non-classical
stuff did
in the converter,
and then Cole
and Hackenberger
figured out
how to do that
into the motor
so they could
do it on site
so that you could
use a classical
power supply,
high-voltage power
supply,
to excite this thing.
Okay,
concerning the batteries,
this is the
early demonstration.
They were going
to go to market
with this thing
as is.
Here it's running
on four golf cart
batteries.
If you'll notice
for this photo,
this battery array
doesn't have
a plastic case on it.
And if you're
wondering,
down here
where the batteries
go,
there's a big
plastic case on it.
That's because
when they got
to the higher
power levels,
these things
started to explode.
The question is,
if they were
exploding batteries,
why the hell
didn't they get
rid of them?
Because
Hackenberger said
they only got
about 67%
of the energy
back to recharge
batteries,
so they have
to have this
generator on there,
which I believe
in this photo
is up there.
So you have
this 30-amp
12-volt generator
topping off
the batteries.
Well,
if this thing's
putting out
7. 5 kilowatts
of mechanical power,
just put a bigger
generator on there
and get rid of
the damn battery.
That didn't happen.
That tells me
that battery
was a very
necessary component
in the system
of this
non-classical
technology.
If you take a look
at the battery
array here,
this idea
that they were
switching batteries
back and forth
is a bunch of
BS because
this array
is not symmetrical.
Notice he's got
all these taps
from 0 to 14 volts
and another set
of batteries
on top of that.
The taps
were used
for speed control.
So apparently
the power supplies
that he had,
you could control
the input voltage,
that would control
the output voltage,
the speed.
That was our
speed controlling
mechanism,
from my best guess.
After the EMA4
came the EMA6.
Now,
for all those people
that think that
the converter element
switching tube
was the heart
and soul
of this technology,
I disagree.
It was an attempt.
But if you'll notice,
this time it's been
removed
and all the switching
is done by
a big commentator.
Let's see,
can you see it
on that front?
No.
Yes,
yes you can.
The switching
is done
over there
in the end
with all those
big white donuts,
all the arcs.
I got pictures
of that thing
arcing and sparking
at night.
So the converter
element switching tubes
originally were designed
to do that switching
and they didn't work
or didn't work as good.
Remember,
when this thing
was debuted,
it only did
two horsepower.
In order to get it
to work,
they had to take that
out and come up
with,
go back again
to mechanical switching.
And then that's
when they generated
all that EMI
and got pinched
by the FCC.
So here's the
battery array here.
Again,
he has that
multiple tap setup,
goes to a big
rotary switch,
that controls the speed,
that controls the input
to those transistor
power inverters.
And at the time,
the CSETs were down here
and those apparently
have been replaced
by the ignitrons
in the later version.
Now,
Aaron and other people
have done a lot of work
with the converter element
switching tube
and come up with
interesting information
and they're working
with ions.
And that is a whole
separate study in itself
and something important
in its own right.
But it was not the foundation
of the great technology.
It was,
in fact,
75 patent shows
related patents
that show the method
of how that switching system
was supposed to work.
But for some reason,
it didn't work
in this application
or it didn't work
as well as something
else could have.
Okay,
the gold motor,
same thing.
Here we got,
down at the bottom,
you can see six batteries there.
You can even see taps.
They needed those
smaller voltage increments
to work with.
And this is in the 1979 era.
That's the sister motor
to this one.
So even now,
they have to have
that other battery.
Okay,
with the photos I had
at the time
before this presentation,
I didn't have pictures
of the battery system in here,
but I assume it was
pretty similar
to the gold motor.
Okay,
so this is
what was shown
in the 1986 patent.
Notice they're showing
two batteries.
By golly,
they're switching them
in and out.
But Peter had it figured out.
They're actually
independent connections.
Now,
maybe you can't switch them,
but it was that battery
that's hooked up
to that capacitor
that kept blowing up.
And how come
they couldn't get rid of it?
They had to have it there.
It served a function.
It provided
charge care,
carriers,
or it provided something
to make this
non-classical technology function.
Here's a schematic
from the 1975 patent,
and it shows
a battery array
that's far more complicated
than that switching
to batteries
back and forth.
So,
the conclusion here,
there's quite a bit
difference from the patent
that was disclosed
and what really is.
Okay,
so here we get down
to hidden secret number four.
This is my favorite.
This is my pet.
Okay,
according to Kenneth Hawkins,
Mr. Hackenberger,
at least in the 1979,
and probably previous,
all the way back
to the beginning,
they used iron wire.
I don't know if they used it
in the primary,
the secondary,
or whatever,
but they used iron wire.
The photographs
from the inside
of the EMA4 motor
show what looks like
copper wire
wound around
the electromagnets.
but iron wire,
like this roll over here,
is available
copper coated.
So then,
I don't know
if they have
copper coated iron wire
that's insulated,
so you can't tell
from the outside
if that's really
copper wire.
But it just so happens
that in my studies
of free energy,
there's other pioneers
that have used
iron wire
in their experiments.
I've already talked
a little bit
about the stubble field device.
Here's one
you might not be familiar with.
This is the
Prentice device.
This is in about 1925.
Anyway,
he has a Tesla coil,
or it can be an RF generator,
running this big delay line,
half a mile long.
It's got to be
nine inches above the ground
or it don't work.
Then he has this,
which is essentially
a radio receiver,
picking up the energy
that comes off this wire
and you get way more energy
off this thing
than you do here
by a factor
of like about 600 watts or so.
Well,
even if this thing did work,
nobody's going to use it.
I mean,
that's kind of impossible
to manage.
But the key takeaway here
is this wire
is telegraph,
common telegraph wire.
Common telegraph wire
is zinc-coated iron wire,
in this case,
10 gauge.
So here he's got
this big line
of iron wire
doing his magic.
Also,
if we get into
the Carlos Benitez project,
he's got
the same sort of things,
a high-voltage
source here,
but he's got it
going into this arc system.
And these arc electrodes
are iron.
They're magnetically excited
and it has another set
of opposing electrodes
that are supposed
to break the arc apart.
So we've got
the same sort of thing.
I don't know
if that was enough iron
to do it
or if there's more iron
in the rest of the system,
but there's enough iron
there to convince me
that it's a possibility.
And it's also,
it generates
its event
on the break
of the arc,
the break
of that high current arc.
And he shows
how he taps off energy,
rectifies it,
and again,
sends it back
to a lead-acid battery,
which I believe
is a necessary component
in the system.
Also,
we've got
Edward Leedscallion,
who wheeled
and dealed
with allegedly
anti-gravity.
These are some
of his remaining
artifacts
that are at
Coral Castle.
And if you look closely,
and other people have,
the wire
that he's got
wrapped around
that bottle
in the center
is rusting,
which implies
that he was also
using iron wire.
So these four
pioneers,
who did,
as far as I could tell,
legitimate work,
but each one
of these systems,
for one reason
or another,
was not commercially
viable,
or nobody understood it,
or you're all
familiar with the problems.
So,
in my case,
I figure it's an idea
worth exploring.
So this is my
current setup here.
This is a reconstructed
stubble field coil
using iron wire
from the garden store
and 12-gauge
copper wire
because they happen
to be the same diameter.
Well,
these are wound
by filer,
so you end up
with this nice
delay line.
So you get some
interesting things
on the scope
when you pulse this.
In my case,
I'm using this
25-horsepower
contactor
with a floor switch.
So you turn it on
and I'm just running.
Here I just show
one battery,
but now I've got
two batteries.
Runs 24 volts
through there.
But that iron wire
is resistive.
It's got 20 ohms,
so I can only get
an amp of current
through there,
which I figure
is far, far short
of the 1,500 amps
that Gray was working with.
But then again,
stubble field
was only working
with like a 2-volt
voltage drop
with his system.
So I'm figuring
maybe we might
get lucky.
And then here's
the outer collection coil.
That thing's got
three Henry's
of inductance in it.
It's from a friend
of mine.
He already had it built,
so that saved me
a lot of work.
So that's what I'm doing
in my off time.
So that wraps it up
for the history
and kind of some
of the technical secrets
I've been able
to figure out.
Now it's a good time
for questions.
Maybe I've explained
this so good.
Hello.
Okay.
So your experiment
there where you
could only get
one amp
through the iron wire.
Right.
Okay.
So if you go back
to the Crosby report,
they said that
the front end
of that thing
only was 26 watts.
Right.
So one amp
isn't a problem.
Probably not.
For the way
the machine
actually worked.
Well,
they ran it
into a converter,
inverter,
and bumped
that voltage
up to a lot higher.
Yeah.
And then they
pulsed it
at 1,500 volts,
3,000, 5,000,
I don't know what.
Right.
And I'm pulsing
it at 24 volts.
Right.
So I don't think
I'm in quite
in the window
of operation.
Yeah.
But I'm trying
to find something
that looks different
enough so I can say,
aha, here's the difference.
We'll try it again
and see if we get
an improvement.
Yeah.
So I'm just...
The thing is
is that at 24 volts
the power
is so weighted
towards magnetism
and so not weighted
towards dielectric
that you're really
not going to find...
Yeah, I'm not in the
right window of operation.
But I figure
Stubblefield was able
to get some action
at that...
I mean,
he was only working
with two volts.
But he had a mechanical
make and break.
Right.
Well, I got a mechanical
make and break, too.
Right.
except it's only one
turn it on, boom,
let it off.
And his was probably
oscillating at 30
to 200 pulses
a second or so.
Anyway, great.
Thank you so much.
We've got a question
from online.
Oh, an online question?
Yes.
Okay.
Could some subtle,
measurable,
possibly ether-related
parameter
in the surrounding
environment
in which the motor
runs
likely affect
the operation
of the motor
and or other
free energy devices?
Oh, I'm sure it does.
Just we don't know
what any of that stuff is.
We can't even measure it.
We haven't described it.
We don't have any units for it.
We don't know
what the relationship is
between its voltage component
if it has one
and its current component
or even has those things.
We are totally in the dark
in what we're working with.
Probably the spiritualist people
are more advanced
in this science
than we are.
Do you know
how many spark gaps
you have
in the prototype,
the gray motor?
In the gray motor?
Well, let's see.
It depends on which one.
This one here,
I believe they only had
the one spark gap
that broke
the high current circuit.
Now, originally,
the earlier ones,
they had spark gaps
in the power supply.
They had spark gaps
in the commentator.
And then they had
the main power break.
So it depends
on which version.
But as the versions
got more modern,
they had fewer
and fewer spark gaps.
But I believe
that a spark gap
is necessary,
just like the battery.
Something in that spark gap.
All those other technologies
I was talking about,
they all have spark gaps
and they all have batteries.
So you had two other follow-ons.
How do you quench
your spark gaps?
And then with regards
to the iron wire,
do you believe
in magnetic currents?
I know
Ledskalonskin did?
I didn't pronounce that part.
Thank you.
Okay.
Let's see.
What was that first one again?
Quenching spark gap.
Okay.
The quenching spark gap
is very, very important.
That's why this motor
has to turn
at a minimum
of 500 RPM
so that the speed
at which those arcs
are pulled apart
is met.
You don't see
very many
dynamic
spark quenching systems.
Tesla used air.
He also used
rotors and commentators
on a much smaller scale.
Here we're working
with a 12-inch motor
that you can actually
calculate the number
of inches per second
that thing is moving.
And that's critical.
If you look at this motor here,
he's got these indices
on the end
that one measures
340,
346,
333.
He's measuring these things
in increments
of 3 degrees
to determine
where the best point is
to quench that arc
or how long it takes
to quench the arc.
You probably have to
start quenching the arc.
You strike the arc,
but you can't quench it
until several milliseconds
later
when the current
has reached its peak.
My replicated
stubble field coil
with all that iron wire
in there
measures 20 henries.
So the rise time
of that current
is pretty slow
on the secondary.
But anyway,
it's done with
physical separation.
And apparently
there's a minimum speed.
You can go a lot faster
than 500 RPM,
but you've got to go
at least 500 RPM
to get this thing
to quench properly.
And then the question
of the iron wire
was what?
With regard to the iron wire,
do you believe
in magnetic currents?
I know
Liedskal...
Yeah, did.
Ed Liedskalnen
of Coral Castle.
Yes.
Yeah, I've read his work
and I can't understand it.
I believe, yes,
we're dealing with
classical engineering dynamics here
when we're talking about
transferring power
from the primary
to the secondary.
And yes,
we have a magnetic component there.
But the magnetic component
is minuscule
compared to the forces
that are generated
from this radiant event
when it takes place.
In fact,
if you calculate
how much magnetic force
you can generate
in this motor,
you can't generate anything
because there's no iron there,
hardly.
And it's an open core thing.
The actual flux
between those poles
is minuscule.
You can't take...
And there's so little iron
that it saturates.
Where in the heck
did all that torque come from?
Well, it didn't come from
classic magnetic repulsion.
Any other questions?
Online or...
A couple more comments.
No spark gaps
in his motor of today?
No, there's the spark gap
between the poles.
Okay.
And then the last one,
could the motor run
at the coral castle?
Could it run
Well, if it was working,
it could run anywhere
as far as I know.
However,
you can't hook
this thing to ground.
It's got to be isolated.
That's why it has
to have the batteries.
Just like John Bedini said,
this particular energy,
if you hook it to ground,
all of it goes to the ground
because that's where
it wants to go.
It'll go through
the positive wire,
it'll go through
the negative wire.
It's just gone.
So that's why
it only works
as an isolated system.
Thank you, Mark McKay.
Thank you very much
for coming.